Back to the slides.
I mentioned that one thing I want to do today
is to discuss expressions vs. commands.
Expressions are things that I discussed in
the whiteboard video.
The mathematical formulas, for example, are
arithmetic expressions.
And commands, on the other hand, are things
like "print" or an assignment in an imperative
language.
Often, expressions are also called "terms",
and commands are often called "statements".
And I think I will use, in both cases, either
terminology, without much thinking, actually.
So, let's think about expression-based programming.
Let me actually first say that for today's
lecture, mainly we are not even doing functional
programming, but the point is more about expression-based
programming.
We will use functions in our expressions.
And also in the first CodeWorld tasks that
you will get, you will use functions.
But you will probably not define your own
functions.
So, it is mainly about building expressions
from functions.
So, what is an expression?
Well, it is as in the statement I just made:
Functional programming is mainly about expressions,
whereas imperative programming is about the
other thing, about commands.
And that is what we saw when I discussed the
differences in the whiteboard video.
What's an expression?
Well, you know many expressions in all
kinds of languages.
For example, arithmetic expressions as occurred
in the video.
So, "2 + 3 × (x+1)^2" or the examples that
I showed in the video.
These are expressions.
Things that are built from symbols, from variables,
constants, and operations.
This is not only something for arithmetics.
For example, in logic, you know propositional
logic formulas that could look like this.
And this is also an expression.
Or, in an Excel spreadsheet, you might use
expressions to describe what should be the
value of a certain cell.
Other examples would be expressions in SQL.
When you do database queries, the language
in which you write them, SQL, is also very
much an expression-based language.
So, these things are built up from parts.
They have a certain syntax.
And you get structured expressions, similarly
to what I showed last week in the CodeWorld
editor, where I also explored the tree underlying
a picture expression.
And indeed, we can write down the syntax trees.
And maybe I will do this on an example in
another short video later.
Generally, mathematically speaking, a term,
an expression, is simply something that is
built from a signature.
So, we have constants, functions/operators,
possibly variables, as discussed earlier in
my other expression examples.
So, what's the point?
What are properties of expressions, or specifically,
of pure expressions?
Later, we will discuss the difference: whether
they are compositional.
As I just said, expressions are built completely
from subexpressions.
So if you take an expression, draw it down
as a tree, and then point at any node in that
tree, then what you get rooted at that point
is just another expression, a subexpression.
That is not true for commands, as we will
see.
Expressions usually have a type, or can be
given a type.
In the example we just saw (the arithmetic
expression), of course all the subexpressions
and also the whole expression had a numerical
type.
Depending on what x might be, it could be
natural numbers or a real numbers, whatever.
But, the point is, we can assign types to
expressions and to their subexpressions.
They usually have a value.
Expressions can be evaluated.
So, we take "2 + 3 × (x+1)^2".
And if you know what x is, if we have (in
scope) a variable x, with which we have a
value assigned, then we know what the value
of the whole expression is.
And this happens without any hidden influences:
If we know the variables, then we know what
the result of an expression is.
And it doesn't change if we evaluate the expression
several times.
If the variables are the same, have the same
values, then the result of evaluation will
always be the same.
Also, the result of evaluation does not depend
on the order in which we evaluate subexpressions.
Therefore, pure expressions: if we have "a
+ b" and "a" and "b" are more complex subexpressions,
then it doesn't matter in which order we evaluate
the left and the right side.
The sum will always be the same.
Again, something that is not in general true
for impure expressions in a language like
C, for example.
And this compositionality is not just syntactical.
It really extends to typing and semantics/evaluation.
So, let's take our very simple example from
two slides ago.
What are the ingredients here?
Well, we have the constants 1, 2, and 3.
They have a type: they are whole numbers.
We have some operators.
They could also be given types.
Usually, in mathematics you don't really write
down the types of these very simple operators.
But of course, you could do that.
And you have binary operations and a unary
operation (the square-operator), and then
if you want to know what the value of "two
plus three times something" is, then we go
through these subexpressions and simply evaluate
all the sub expressions, and then accumulate
the results.
This, of course, is all very trivial.
That's exactly what you do when you calculate
with simple arithmetic expressions.
The point here is that this extends to all
the other examples of expressions we have
seen.
And, in particular, it applies to every Haskell
program.
So for Haskell programs their semantics is
only given by evaluation.
And that's definitely not true in imperative
languages.
The examples we saw last week, with the pictures,
were just one instantiation of this.
Okay.
What does this buy us?
Also, again, somehow relating to the whiteboard
video that I did previously.
Well, we can use all kinds of notations from
mathematics.
So, a simple thing like if you have "2 + 3
× (something)^2", we might as well write this
as "2 + 3 × (y^2)" and give a name to that
subexpression.
So, a trivial thing in this case, but for
more complex programs such naming of arbitrary
subexpressions is a valuable thing.
You will see this when you build more complex
Haskell programs, for example.
Again, something that's not immediate and
not always possible in a command-based language,
as you will see.
And, as I have actually already demonstrated
with the "read() + read()" example on the whiteboard,
we can apply simplifications.
So, for example, maybe y^2 is an expensive
operation, and we could instead multiply y
with y.
Well, of course, mathematically, that is okay.
That is exactly the same as here.
Why?
Because y is a variable that's always, in
scope, having the same value.
It is like the "f(x) + f(x) is 2 × f(x)" example
from my previous video.
So, of course, again, it might seem trivial,
applied to arithmetic expressions.
But the point is that these concepts apply
much more generally, if we buy into the notion
that we should program only with functions
and expressions.
If we stay away from impure expressions, if
we stay away from commands, then we can apply
everything we know from algebra.
Everything we know from mathematics, in terms
of manipulating formulas, rearranging formulas,
etc.
All these things can be applied to programs,
if programs are just built from expressions.
This last point is the important thing here:
This applies if you have only pure expressions.
In what sense is this different from imperative
programming?
So, why is what I just said only true in certain
kinds of programs, that we are aiming for
at the moment (expression-based programs)?
Well, let's have a look.
This is some prototypical imperative programming
code.
So, this could be C or Java.
It could also be Python with a little bit
of manipulation or few changes in syntax.
Certainly, we also have expressions here,
right?
So, I mean: This constant is an expression.
This addition here looks like an expression.
We have expressions in the condition of this
while-loop.
Here, we have, again, an arithmetic expression
which calculates something.
So, what's different now?
Well, the point is that of course there are
expression here as well, but they are not
the dominating syntactical construct.
There are many things in this piece of
program code that are not expressions.
For example, "while" is a keyword.
The assignment here is a command.
On the right side we have an expression, but
as a whole, this line here is not an expression.
So, it's not true that everything is, syntactically,
composed of the same kind of construct like
in a purely expression-based language (and
like really in mathematics).
Why is this relevant?
What properties do commands not have that
we know from expressions?
Well, they are not compositional.
So, it's not the case that if you have a command,
then all its smaller-size-contained parts
are themselves commands.
That's already not true in this thing:
This loop is certainly a command, as a whole,
and there are commands inside.
But, for example, this here is not a command.
We have expressions, keywords, etc., as highlighted
on the previous slide.
Moreover, commands do not always have a meaningful
type.
For example, it's not clear what the type
of this command is.
It doesn't really compute a value.
Indeed, it doesn't have value.
So, some expressions here have a value.
This, for example, depending on what "b" is,
will evaluate to "true" or "false".
But the loop as a whole doesn't have a value.
There is no really meaningful way to say what
the value should be.
Or it would be a trivial value.
The same for some subparts: Let's only take
the block from here to here.
This is a sequence of statements, but it is
not something that has a value.
Why?
Because for a command, the important thing
is what effect it has.
So, if you look at this assignment here, what's
interesting to the programmer about this is
that j will afterwards have a different value
than before.
But the statement itself doesn't have an interesting
value.
As a consequence, also, of this lack of compositionality,
we cannot, as previously in mathematics, name
arbitrary well-formed smaller parts.
So, we cannot write the previous example like
that.
Previously, you had this loop: while something
... and then we had this code block.
And we cannot really, in most imperative languages,
give a name to this code block, and then simply
mention the name here.
Because this is not an expression.
So, in C or Java, or Python, the things that
you would consider expressions are the things
that you can write on the right-hand side
of an assignment statement.
And something like this is not something that
you could write.
Of course, this block is not an expression.
It doesn't have a value.
It doesn't have a meaningful type, etc.
You could try some workarounds.
You could use functions, procedures, methods,
depending on the specific language that you're
trying to do this in.
So, you could try to introduce a new procedure
which, essentially, corresponds to this code
block here.
But even then, you don't get the same kind
of flexibility that we are used to from mathematics.
There, we can simply take some expression,
give it a name, and use notation and understand
notation in this spirit here.
So, what about the expressions that do occur
in C or Java or Python?
So, even if not everything is an expression,
at least we know that there are expressions
in these languages as well.
The things that occur on the right-hand sides
of an assignment command, for example.
What about those expressions?
Let's consider the sublanguage of only expressions
in something like C or Java.
Can they at least be treated as we saw before?
So, do we get back our mathematical principles,
if we focus only on the expression part of
an imperative language?
Well, I claim here that it is not the case.
Why is that?
Well, let's look at an example.
It is a bit convoluted here, but really corresponds
to something similar we saw before with concrete
numbers and constants.
So let's look at an expression like this,
which is built from expressions: "subexpression1
+ subexpression2 × (expression3)^2".
We saw that before with constants and some
x + 1 here.
Mathematically, we know that here are three
equivalent ways of writing this piece of expressions.
So, we could really say, for example, name
this expression with some variable name, and
simply square that variable.
Or we could say, squaring that variable is
the same as writing variable × variable.
Or, indeed, we could avoid naming the subexpression,
and simply repeat that subexpression
here.
So, "exp1 + exp2 × exp3 × exp3".
That should also be mathematically equivalent
to this piece of code.
But is it true?
In an imperative setting, if we have this,
for example, as the right-hand side of an
assignment statement, so the very same expression
as we had here, and then, for example, this
"naming a sub expression" could be expressed
in theory as saying:
Well, let's assign the value of the subexpression
to a variable.
(It should be in scope, of course.)
And then let's, in the spirit of this first
line here, for example, have this right-hand
side expression for our result assignment,
in which we square the value of that variable.
That looks like the step from this to this
line.
Or we could try the same for these other two
lines.
Is this a valid transformation in C or Java
or Python?
No, it is not.
Let us consider these four lines here.
Each of them corresponds to one of the hypothetical
reformulations of the expression that we saw
on the previous slide, on the mathematical
level.
And now, we can try them out in an imperative
language, and see whether they behave the
same.
In the sense that in any larger program, I
could replace the line like this by a line
like this, or this, or this, and see whether
I have the same program behaviour.
And if you try this out, you will find out
that, actually, from those four, only the
second and third line will really behave the
same.
Whichever other pair of lines you pick, you
will be able to choose expressions, and maybe
variable values that are used in those expressions,
or function calls that are occurring in these
expressions, and replaced by or tied to specific
implementations of procedures and functions,
and you will be able to observe differences.
The way of convincing yourself of that would
be to replace the exp3 (the expression that
we wanted to give a name to), and then reuse,
for example, in these lines here:
Imagine that exp3 is the so-called expression
"i++", which isn't really an expression.
It is really a statement.
It is a command to increment the value of
the variable "i", which should be in the scope
somehow.
And, for example, if you look at the first
line and the last line, then you will see
that here the "i" will be incremented once,
and here the "i" will be incremented twice.
Which is already an observable difference
from the outset of this expression or these
small program parts.
So, they are not interchangeable.
And the same applies to other pairs.
Or, you don't need to have state manipulations,
you don't need to have an update of a variable.
You could simply have a function call to something
which, ostensibly, is a function, but actually
is not a function in a mathematical sense.
A procedure in your language which might alter
some global state.
It might be a method that you call on an object,
and it changes instance variables of the object.
Then again, taking this first line and the
last line, you will be able to observe differences.
Or "f" is a procedure that does input/output
as in the "print" or "read" examples that
I discussed in a previous video.
Again, things will simply change the semantics.
And that is because what we see here are not
pure expressions.
Because in an imperative language, we don't
have pure expressions.
We have these expressions which have a side
effect.
Which are really commands.
So, we cannot name parts of expressions arbitrarily
or freely.
This is really the underlying problem here.
That even the sublanguage of expressions in
an imperative language is not expression-based,
in the sense of mathematical expressions.
So, despite these lines here originating from
seemingly mathematical equivalences, they
are not program equivalences.
And for the same reason, for example, reevaluating
an expression can lead to different values.
Or the order of evaluating subexpressions
becomes relevant, because we don't really
have functions.
A mathematical function would be where whenever
you call the function with the same input,
you get the same output.
But for a procedure, for a method in an imperative
language, that is not necessarily the case.
You only have to think about the "read" function/method/procedure.
You can call it 10 times, and you can get
10 different results.
That clearly runs counter to any argument
about equivalence of syntactic expressions.
A natural question now is: How bad is this?
Or is it bad at all?
I have shown you quite artificial examples
that demonstrate that in a typically impure,
imperative language, you cannot characterize
expressions or subexpressions by their value.
So, we don't have properties that we know
from mathematics.
Where we can name subexpressions in a term.
Where we can rearrange expressions.
Where we can replace each expression by another
expression, if it has the same value.
So all these properties, also often called
"referential transparency", do not apply in
a typical impure language with side effects.
But does that prove anything?
So, should we bother?
Well, at the moment that is not really the
point.
I haven't yet argued that the pure expression-based
style is better in some sense.
The argument that I have been making, what
is hopefully clear now (or should become more
and more clear), is that these two styles
are different.
Whether one of them is better is a different
question.
But this observation, that things we are used
to from mathematics and from algebra, from
transforming formulas, are not directly applicable
to impure programs in an imperative language.
That is something which really separates it
from mathematics or from a mathematical style
of programming (which both functional and
also logic programming will largely be about).
At the moment, what I wanted to convey is
this difference, not a notion of "better".
That is really the motivation for this course.
While this was, on the other hand, also quite
abstract.
So, my plan is that I will again, beside the
slides here, make some additional video or
videos.
Probably one on the whiteboard again, discussing
some of the compositionality aspects I mentioned
earlier, and then also again an example in
CodeWorld.